Guide to the D. Cady Eaton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
D. Cady Eaton papers
1853-1914
MS 4
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(19 boxes)
Correspondence, notebooks, journals, lectures, drafts of articles and books, and other writings of D. Cady Eaton, art historian, social commentator, and professor at Yale. Included are a number of articles of a philosophical and satirical nature written for the New Haven Journal and Courier.
Eaton, D. Cady (Daniel Cady), 1837-1912
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Special Files.
Scope and Contents
The D. Cady Eaton Papers are divided into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Special Files. The Correspondence series contains fifty-nine letters addressed to Eaton. Correspondents of note are Leonard Bacon (a prominent Congregational clergyman) and Noah Porter, president of Yale University.
The Writings series makes up the bulk of the papers. The material is divided into five sections: (a) Books, which served as a basis for the published works mentioned above, consisting of notebooks on modern French painting and sculpture; (b) Articles, of a philosophical, sometimes satirical nature, written for the New Haven Journal and Courier, usually signed "Periander," 1894-1895, 1897-1901, 1903, 1908, 1910; (c) Lectures on the history of art contained in approximately one hundred notebooks, mostly undated; (d) Journals pertaining to Eaton's travels in Europe, 1853-1854, and England, 1877-1878; and (e) Writings of Others, 1908, 1913-1914, n.d.
Biographical / Historical
D. Cady Eaton* (Daniel Cady Eaton) was born in Johnstown, New York, June 16, 1837, the son of Daniel Cady and Harriet Eliza (Cady) Eaton. He received his B.A. degree from Yale in 1860 and his LL.B. degree from Albany (New York) Law School in 1861. On December 17, 1861 Eaton married Alice Young. From 1861 to 1863 he served in the New York militia, retiring with the rank of colonel. Eaton practiced law in New York until 1866. From 1867 to 1870 he studied the history of art, first at the University of Berlin, and then in Paris. He was appointed Professor of History and Criticism of Art at Yale University in 1869, a position he held until he resigned in 1876. Eaton returned to Yale in 1902 and was made professor emeritus in 1909. He was the author of three books: Handbook of Greek and Roman Sculpture (1884), Handbook of Modern French Painting (1909), and Handbook of Modern French Sculpture (published posthumously in 1913). He died in New Haven May 11, 1912.
Additional biographical material may be found in Who Was Who in America, 1897-1942, Appleton's Cyclopaedia of American Biography, and the Yale Alumni Weekly, May 1912.
* Professor Eaton always used the initial D. in place of Daniel in order to distinguish himself from his cousin, Daniel Cady Eaton (1834-1895), a botanist and also a professor at Yale.
Separated Materials
In addition to his published books, the following printed pamphlets by D. Cady Eaton are catalogued as part of the collections of Sterling Memorial Library:
"Introduction to the Study of Greek Sculpture." An Address. (New Haven, 1878) (In Greek Archaeology, V. I)
"Introduction to the Study of Greek Sculpture," 1878
"Pensions." New Haven, 1893 (originally published in the New Haven Register
Report to Messrs. Bacon and Twichell, appointed June, 1875, committee to investigate the affairs of the Art School. (New Haven, 1875)
The Study of the Arts of design in American Colleges... New Haven, 1882
Yale College in 1881. Four articles by an "Alumnus" reprinted from the New Haven Evening Register
Yale College in 1890, Reflections on its charter, 1890
"Unconstitutional Coinage" (n.p., n.d.)
Art -- History; Art; Satire, American; Travelers -- United States; Europe -- Description and travel; Europe; Art historians; Eaton, D. Cady (Daniel Cady), 1837-1912; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1860; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Fine Arts
- Correspondence, 1861-1879; Series I; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name. There are fifty-nine letters addressed to D. Cady Eaton, as well as approximately ten drafts of letters in Eaton's hand. The latter is at the end of the series.
  - Bacon, Leonard, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brewer, William H., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Child, Calvin G., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Churchill, Richard C., 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DeForest, J. W., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Farnam, Henry, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goodyear, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hawley, H. E., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hoppice, J. M., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - McAlpine, N., 1879 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mitchell, D. G., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Phelps, G. D., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Porter, Noah, 1871-1872, 1874-1876 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robbins, H., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Selmes, T. R., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Taylor, Alfred J., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Towle, George Makepeace, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Weir, J. F., 1871-1872, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wheeler, C., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Woolsey, J. D., 1869, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Young, Henry, 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Young, Mason, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Drafts of Letters by D. Cady Eaton, 1872, 1874-1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings, 1881-1914; Series II; 7.25 linear feet (17 boxes)
  This series is divided into five sections: Books, Articles, Lectures, Journals, and Writings of Others. Under the Books section there are fifteen numbered notebooks on modern French painting and fourteen numbered notebooks on modern French sculpture, which are preliminary drafts of Eaton's books, Handbook of Modern French Painting (1909) and Handbook of Modern French Sculpture (1913).
  In the Articles section there are forty-five pieces arranged alphabetically by title. These articles, dated between 1894 and 1910, represent the world situation as Eaton saw it. Most of the are signed "Periander" and are addressed to the editor of the New Haven Journal and Courier.
  There are approximately one hundred notebooks in the Lectures section dealing with the history of art. The notebooks are arranged under the name of the country or the geographical area with which their contents deal. These headings include: "Egypt," "England," "France," "Germany," "Greece," "Italy," and the "Near East." There are thirteen notebooks in this section which are concerned with aesthetics and art forms. They are grouped under the heading "Miscellaneous." Most of the notebooks are undated.
  The Journals section contains two items in Eaton's hand. The first records a trip to Europe in 1853-1854. The second records a sojourn in England from April 9, 1877 to June 1, 1878.
  There are three items in the Writings of Others section.
  - Books
    - Handbook of Modern French Painting /Notebook A, Watteau-Gros
      - Notebook A, Watteau-Gros (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Notebook I, Landscape (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Notebook no. 1, Fragonard (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Notebook no. 1, Addenda (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Notebook no. 2, Gros-Chavennes (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Notebook no. 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Notebook no. 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Notebook no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Notebook no. 6 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Notebook no. 7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Notebook no. 8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Notebook no. 9, 3rd Republic (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Notebook no. 10, 3rd Republic (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Notebook no. 11, 3rd Republic (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Notebook, Index of Provincial Museums (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Handbook of Modern French Sculpture
      - Notebook no. 1, Introduction, Hegel, Newberry (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Notebook no. 2, Introduction, Hegel (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Notebook I, Introduction (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Notebook II, Introduction cont. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Notebook III (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Notebook IV (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Notebook V, XVIII century (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Notebook VI, 1787-1852 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Notebook VI, cont. (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Notebook VII, 2nd Empire (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Notebook VIII, cont. of X (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Notebook IX (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - Notebook X, XIX and XX centuries (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - Notebook, Paris Monuments and Memorial Statues (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Articles
    - "At Sea with Dunraven", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "A Breeze from Litchfield", 1894 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Cat's Paw Made of France", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - "Coal Combination", 1910 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - "A Confession of Faith", 1910 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - "Cornell's Crew Watched", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - "Corporation Evils", 1908 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - "Delights of Munich Beer", 1900 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - "The Duty of Democracy", 1903 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - "Franco-Russian Alliance", 1897 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - "Full-Fledged Yeller", 1894 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - "Getting Away from Dust", 1894 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - "Gossip from Litchfield", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "Governor Ingersoll", 1903 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - "Great Britain's Royalty", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - "Grief in Litchfield", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - "If Art Does Not Please, It Fails of Its Mission", 1900 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - "Is Litchfield Aristocratic?", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "It Was an Utter Fizzle", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - "Life as Seen in Dinard", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - "Litchfield Beauty", 1908 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - "Litchfield Expert on Eggs", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - "Litchfield in Millennium", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - "Litchfield Peculiarities", 1899 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - "Litchfield Thunder Storms", 1899 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - "Litchfield's Exclusive Set", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - "A Look from Prospect Hill", 1894 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - "The Markets of Ostend", 1895 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - "The Matter of Mosquitos and Fog-A Scientist", 1898 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - "Nectar Fit for the Gods", 1901 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - "Paris, for Paris, Is Quiet", 1897 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - "Periander in England", 1897 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - "Periander in New York", 1899 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - "Periander in Stuttgart", 1900 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - "The Plaint of a Traveler", 1895 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - "Professor Eaton Warns Nation", 1910 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - "Prospect is Disappointing", 1900 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Quotations, undated (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - "The Sharon that is in Connecticut", 1899 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - "Spain's Responsibility", 1898 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - "The Stir in Litchfield", 1897 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - "Straddle Run in Football", 1899 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - "The Suicide of Chinese Officials", 1901 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - "To the Democratic Party", 1900 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - "Tribute from a Brother", 1895 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - "Woes of a Resorter", 1894 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Lectures - Egypt
    - Notebook I, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Notebook III, undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Notebook IV, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Land of the Pharaohs, Typescript, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Lectures - England
    - Canterbury Cathedral, notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Durham Cathedral, notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Ely Cathedral, notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Gothic Architecture, notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Lectures - France
    - Charles VII, VIII, typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Charles VIII, typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Charles VIII, Louis XII, Francis I, Book V, notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Chateau de Blois, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Christian Iconography, illustrated from Amien's Cathedral, notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - The Evolution of the French Chateau, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Expedition of Charles VIII to Italy, notebook, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Francis I, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - French History, Part II, notebook, undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - French History, Part III, notebook, undated (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - French History, Part IV, notebook, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Index to French Slides, notebook, undated (Box 8, Folder 95-97)
    - Index to French Slides - Sculpture, notebook, undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Louis XII, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - The Louvre, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - Mont St. Michel, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 9, Folder 101-102)
    - Mont St. Michel, Sup., notebook, undated (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Notre Dame de Paris, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Notre Dame de Paris, no. 2, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Rheims, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Lectures - Germany
    - Frederick the Great, Part V, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Hohenzollern, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Hohenzollern, I, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Hohenzollern, II, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Hohenzollern, III, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Hohenzollern, IV, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Hohenzollern, VI, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 113)
    - Hohenzollern, VII, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Notes on German History, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Lecture - Greece
    - Apollo, Lecture 8, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - The Greater Divinities, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Greek Temple, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Greek Temple, cont., notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - History of Greek Sculpture I, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - History of Greek Sculpture II, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic II, notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic II, cont., and beginning of III, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic III, cont., notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 124-125)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic IV, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic IV, cont., notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic IV, New Series, Athens I, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic V, Athens II, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - History of Greek Sculpture, Traditional and Archaic VI, Athens III, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - History of Greek Sculpture VI to VII, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - History of Greek Sculpture VII, Athens IV, notebook, undated (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - The Laocoon, typescript & notebook, 1881 (Box 12, Folder 133)
    - Late Discoveries in Greece, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Late Discoveries in Greece II notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - Late Discoveries in Greece III notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Late Discoveries in Greece IV notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Notes on Schaase (History of the Fine Arts under Greeks & Romans), notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Olymphia Delphi, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Polycletus (Amazons), notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Praxiteles, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Roman Period, Lecture 10, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 142-143)
    - Snake Goddess from Crete, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Venus of Milo, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Miscellaneous - Adriadne, Fauns …, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Miscellaneous - Art No. 1, notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Lectures - Italy
    - Catherine de Medici, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - Cities of Norther Italy, typescript, 1898 (Box 14, Folder 149)
    - Este and Gonzaga Letters, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 150)
    - Isabella d'Este and Gonzaga, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Isabella Este and her son, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - Italian Painting I, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 153)
    - Italian Painting II & II sup., notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - Italian Painting III, notebook, undated (Box 14, Folder 155)
    - Italian Painting IV & IV sup., notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 156)
    - Italian Painting IV notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 157)
    - Italian Painting V notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 158)
    - Italian Painting VI notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 159)
    - Italian Painting VII notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - Italian Painting VIII notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Italian Painting IX notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - Italian Painting X notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 163)
    - Italian Painting XI notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - Italian Painting XII notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 165)
    - Italian Painting supplement, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 166)
    - Leonardo da Vinci, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 167)
    - Ludovico el Moro and Beatrice d'Este, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 168)
    - Mantua, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 169)
    - Northern Italy Cities, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 170)
    - Padua, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 171)
    - Rome, notebook, undated (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - Lectures - Near East - Chaldea, Assyria, Persia, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 173)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Aesthetics, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 174)
    - Aesthetics of Common Life, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 175)
    - Architecture, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 176)
    - Arts of Design, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 177)
    - The Beautiful, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 178)
    - Chocolate; A Friend's Tribute, typescript, 1881 (Box 17, Folder 179)
    - De la Science du Beau - Voituron, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 180)
    - Gothic Art fragment, typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 181)
    - Notes for a New Bausteine, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 182)
    - Perpendicular Gothic, notebook, undated (Box 17, Folder 183)
    - Renaissance, notebook, undated (Box 18, Folder 184)
    - The Science of Art Form, typescript & notebook, undated (Box 18, Folder 185)
    - Talks for 1903-1904, Renaissance cont., architecture notebook, undated (Box 18, Folder 186)
  - Journals
    - Journal of a voyage in Europe, 1853-1854 (Box 18, Folder 187)
    - Journal of a sojourn in England, 1877-1878 (Box 18, Folder 188)
  - Writings of others
    - History notebook by K.H. Willoughby, undated (Box 18, Folder 189)
    - Literature 12, notebook and exam papers, 1908, 1913-1914 (Box 18, Folder 190)
    - "Songs of the Cid" by Mrs. F. Hemans, undated (Box 18, Folder 191)
- Special Files, 1853-1912; Series III; 0.5; (1 box)
  The Special Files series contains a certificate of life membership in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, college papers, an expense book, two catalogs of books, a reprint from the American Journal of Science, a sketch book, the May 1912 issue of the Yale Alumni Weekly, and notes on the Yale School of Fine Arts, Items in this series are arranged alphabetically by type.
  - Certificates of Life Membership in the Metropolitan Museum of Art; certificates of admission to the bar, 1861, 1878, 1911 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - College papers, compositions, debates, poems, 1859, 1860, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Expense book, 1911 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Library of the Fine Arts (catalog of books), undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Reprint from the American Journal of Science, 1912 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Sketch book, 1870 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified library (catalog of books), undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Yale Alumni Weekly, 1912 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Yale School of Fine Arts: miscellaneous notes, 1871, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)